and your favorite musician 10 years ago. I put mine up on the screen to help you along. Now we asked people to predict for us, to tell us how much money they would pay right now to see their current favorite musician perform in concert 10 years from now, and on average, people said they would pay 129 dollars for that ticket. And yet, when we asked them how much they would pay to see the person who was their favorite 10 years ago perform today, they say only 80 dollars. Now, in a perfectly rational world, these should be the same number, but we overpay for the opportunity to indulge our current preferences because we overestimate their stability. Why does this happen? We're not entirely sure, but it probably has to do with the ease of remembering versus the difficulty of imagining. Most of us can remember who we were 10 years ago, but we find it hard to imagine who we're going to be, and then we mistakenly think that because it's hard to imagine, it's not likely to happen. Sorry, when people say "I can't imagine that," they're usually talking about their own lack of imagination, and not about the unlikelihood of the event that they're describing. The bottom line is, time is a powerful force. It transforms our preferences. It reshapes our values. It alters our personalities. We seem to appreciate this fact, but only in retrospect. Only when we look backwards do we realize how much change happens in a decade. It's as if, for most of us, the present is a magic time. It's a watershed on the timeline. It's the moment at which we finally become ourselves. Human beings are works in progress that mistakenly think they're finished. The person you are right now is as transient, as fleeting and as temporary as all the people you've ever been. The one constant in our life is change. Thank you. (Applause)
y el de hace 10 años. Yo pongo el mío en la pantalla para ayudarles. Ahora le pedimos a las personas que predigan, que nos cuenten, cuánto dinero pagarían ahora para ver a su artista favorito actual en un concierto dentro de 10 años, y, en promedio, dijeron que pagarían USD 129 por esa entrada. Y cuando les preguntamos cuánto pagarían para ver actuar hoy a quien fue su artista favorito hace 10 años, dijeron que solo pagarían USD 80. En un mundo perfectamente racional, este debería ser el mismo número, pero pagamos de más por la oportunidad de satisfacer nuestras preferencias actuales porque sobreestimamos su estabilidad. ¿Por qué ocurre esto? No estamos totalmente seguros, pero probablemente tenga que ver con la facilidad de recordar versus la dificultad de imaginar. Muchos podemos recordar quiénes éramos hace 10 años, pero nos resulta difícil imaginar quiénes seremos, y entonces pensamos erróneamente que como es difícil de imaginar, no es probable que suceda. Lo siento, cuando decimos "No puedo imaginarlo", por lo general hablamos de nuestra propia falta de imaginación y no de la falta de probabilidad de los eventos que describimos. Como conclusión: el tiempo es una fuerza poderosa. Transforma nuestras preferencias. Retoca nuestros valores. Altera nuestras personalidades. Parece que apreciamos este hecho, pero solo en retrospectiva. Solo al mirar hacia atrás nos damos cuenta del gran cambio ocurrido en una década. Es como si, para muchos de nosotros, el presente fuese un tiempo mágico. Es una divisoria de aguas en la línea de tiempo. Es el momento en el cual finalmente nos tornamos nosotros mismos. Los seres humanos somos obras en curso y por error pensamos que estamos concluidos. La persona que uno es ahora es tan transitoria, fugaz y temporal como todas las personas que uno ha sido. Lo único constante en nuestra vida es el cambio. Gracias. (Aplausos)